In the next concepts,
في المفاهيم التالية،
we are going to combine what we know about how to calculate the mean with notation.
سنقوم بدمج ما نعرفه عن كيفية حساب المتوسط من خلال الترميز.
The purpose of this video is not to relearn how to calculate the mean
لا يهدف هذا الفيديو إلى إعادة معرفة كيفية حساب المتوسط،
but rather to introduce notation using a measure you already know.
وإنما تقديم الترميز باستخدام مقياس تعرفه بالفعل.
Let's consider the amount of time someone spends on our website in minutes.
لنفكر مثلًا في مقدار الوقت الذي يقضيه أحد الأشخاص على موقع الويب بالدقائق.
Imagine we collect the amount of time spent on our site for five individuals.
وتخيل أننا نجمع مقدار الوقت الذي يقضيه خمسة أشخاص على موقع الويب خاصتنا.
From the last video,
من خلال الفيديو السابق،
we saw that we could label the values in this way,
رأينا أنه يمكننا تسمية القيم بهذه الطريقة،
x1 for the first value,
تشير x1 إلى القيمة الأولى،
x2 for the second value,
وتشير x2 إلى القيمة الثانية،
x3 for the third value and so on.
بينما تشير x3 إلى القيمة الثالثة وهكذا.
Imagine we want to add the first two numbers together.
تخيل أننا نريد إضافة العددين الأولين معًا.
We could write this in notation as x1 plus x2 which in this example,
يمكننا كتابة هذا في ترميز بالشكل التالي، x1 زائد x2 كما في هذا المثال،
would be the same as 15 plus 10.
وسينطبق الأمر نفسه على 15 زائد 10.
If we wanted to add more than just two values,
أما إذا أردنا إضافة أكثر من قيمتين،
it would be tedious to continue the same process.
فسيكون من الممل مواصلة العملية نفسها.
Imagine if we had 100 values.
تخيل لو كان لدينا 100 قيمة.
We would have a, x1 plus x2 plus x3
سنحصل على x1 زائد x2 زائد x3
plus and we'd have to continue this process until x 100.
وسيتعين علينا متابعة هذه العملية وصولًا إلى x 100.
Someone must have come up with a better way to notate this.
يجب أن يكون شخص ما قد توصل إلى طريقة أفضل لترميز ذلك.
And it turns out, there is a better way.
وها قد اتضح ذلك، توجد طريقة أفضل.